Okay, and we're away. Um, welcome
everybody to the third episode of Active
Inference Insights brought to you by the
Active Inference Institute. I'm your
host Daryus Parvis Wayne and today I am
absolutely thrilled to be able to speak
to John Vivei. John is an award-winning
professor of psychology, cognitive
science, and Buddhist philosophy at the
University of Toronto. He is also the
presenter of the renowned YouTube series
Awakening from the Meaning Crisis, as
well as the newer after Socrates. His
work focuses on 4E cognitive science,
which holds that cognition is embodied,
embedded, enacted, and extended beyond
the brain. In particular, John explores
relevance realization, our adaptive
ability to zero in on salient
information in a world of near infinite
complexity. Last year, he, Mark Miller,
and Brett Anderson wrote the paper
predictive processing and relevance
realization, exploring convergent
solutions to the frame problem, which
proposes that trade off uh trade-offs in
precision waiting, a key second order
dynamic in predictive processing
hierarchies are at the heart of our
ability to be intelligently ignorant.
And that alignment of predictive
processing and relevance realization is
exactly what we're going to be talking
about today. John, welcome to the show.
Thank you so much for joining us. It's
an absolute treat. Thank you, Darius.
Uh, a great pleasure. Um, I'm, uh,
hoping that Mark does make it on in
December. Uh, that'll be great.
Yeah, absolutely. But in his absence,
because Mark was me meant to be here
today, but it's, uh, unfortunat he's not
unfortunately able to make it. Um,
perhaps. So this podcast is acting as a
kind of primer and introduction for our
audience to the critical themes in
cognitive science and psychology and
biology as well as maths and physics as
they are right now. Um so I think it
would be a worthwhile uh worthwhile
place to start if you could just unpick
what relevance realization is and then
we'll come to how it aligns with
predictive processing.
Sure. Uh so relevance realization is
um sort of inverts the way common sense
works. Common sense is there's a lot
that is obvious to us and we know what
it's obvious what we should pay
attention to. We're sometimes mistaken
but it's obvious what we should be
remembering and what we should be doing
and that's all obvious and we just run
from that. Um, our job as cognitive
scientists is to explain how the brain
generates that obviousness
that salience landscapes that makes the
right things stand out as relevant to us
so that we can do what is astonishing
solve a wide variety of problems in a
wide variety of domains. Um, you're a
general problem solver which is just
astonishing. I mean, you can learn
Albanian history. You could learn about
swimming or rock climbing. You can take
up the study of dinosaurs in the
Jurassic period. Like, it's just, you
know, and it's just amazing and
astonishing. And there's good empirical
evidence. You have something like a
general intelligence. There seems to be
a general capacity. There's individual
variation in talent. Some people are
better at learning this domain than
other domains. But there way back from
Spearman, we know there's some sort of
general ability. Uh I'm going to propose
that the general ability are two
interlocking things. The anticipation
and relevance realization. What I mean
by a general ability is the these are
kind of meta problems. These are the two
big problems you have to solve when
you're doing any other specific problem
solving. And what makes relevance
realization so hard generating that
obviousness so mysterious? Actually,
that's what Scott Atrin says. say he he
says that what science does is it makes
what common sense to take takes to be
obvious mysterious here's a table in
front of me but physics says well what
is that really and mysterious and it's
made out of quarks and all this sort of
stuff it's the same sort of thing here
because when you think about it um
outside of common sense you realize that
there's just an overwhelming amount of
information that's constantly as you
said dynamically changing in the
environment there's an overwhelming
amount of information in your long-term
memory that's constantly changing and
being readjusted during due to the
reconstructive nature of memory. There
is an overwhelming number of
combinations of actions you can perform,
sequences of actions. And yet you ignore
that overwhelming
almost all of that overwhelming
information and zero in on the relevant
information so that you are oriented it
right in the world. Finding things
obvious, salient, standing out and
you're and and it's and it's not just a
single thing. There's like a salience
landscape. Some things stand out more
than others. Some things are more
foreground, background. You have all
this happening. So that you are capable
of solving so many problems in a messy
complex world in which there's constant
novelty because of emergent phenomena.
And trying to give this ability to
machines has been overwhelmingly
uh difficult and one of the hard hard
problems. We're actually bumping up
right into it now as we've finally taken
up the AGI project, the project of
trying to create artificial general
intelligence.
Excellent. Um, it may be worth digging a
little bit deeper into that exposition.
Um, because people might be thinking,
well, don't we just have a module for
relevance or salience? So we just kind
of were born and we know oh um I should
not fall off cliffs and I should but
actually what happened yesterday might
be quite irrelevant. You have a
wonderful um explanation in your sort of
keynote paper explicating relevance
realization where you say that leads to
an infinite regress. Um
perhaps you could explain that uh
argument. So the magic module not to be
confused with predictive processing's
purported problem of the magic
modulator. So let's keep those two
distinct from each other. But the magic
the magic module is well I have a I have
a relevance realization thing in my head
that just does it. And then that just
and then I can just say well how does it
do it? And the mistake people can make
is well evolution made it. And that's
right. Evolution tells me how it got
here. That's not telling me how it
functions. Evolution tells me how my eye
got here and how my ear got here. And
that's not telling me how my eye and my
ear function. I'm trying to take what's
called the design stance. How could tell
me what I need to do to give that module
the ability to realize relevance. You
you all you've done is said it has that
ability, but it faces the problem of
okay, now it has to know what to pay
attention to and so on and so forth.
Now, what you might say is, "Well,
evolution totally prepared us for it."
The problem with that is that doesn't
work. Uh, evolution can only pick up on
things that are long-term invariant and
that make an ongoing continuous
um difference to your reproductive uh
status, right? And that's not how
relevance works. Relevance is really
fast and changing. If I say left big
toe, it suddenly becomes relevant to you
and it wasn't relevant a minute ago. And
what's the Darwinian difference there?
Um, and there's nothing that's
intrinsically relevant. Well, my own
life is intrinsically relevant. Is it?
You'll sacrifice your life for your
kids. Well, my life and my kids, but
under all circumstances, you know what?
If you know, saving your kid means that
10 million people, oh, well, and so on.
And we get into all these philosophical
arguments because we realize, no, no,
there isn't any hard fast thing that is
always relevant. Relevance is not
something for which we can generate a
scientific theory. It's not stable. It's
not intrinsic to the phenomena. And it
there's nothing other than being
relevant. There's nothing that all the
events or objects or feelings have in
common. Like what is it that what do
they all have that makes them other than
saying, "Well, they're you'll give me
synonyms. They're important to me or
they help me solve my problems." Yes,
that's exactly it. But how? But how?
Exactly. Perfect. And it's it's so nice
to see how the um apparently disperate
strands of cognitive science so
Gibsonian affordances for e cognitive
science predictive processing processing
and active inference align at this path
which is that everything is dynamical.
Everything is about this mutual
unfolding. There is no raified static um
existence. It's what's relevant to you
might not be relevant to me and there
are these dynamic relationships which
govern that. Um it's yeah so that's
that's a that's a great place to start I
think let's now go into uh the solution
if there is such a such a solution and
let's start with opponent processing. So
this is a term that you use frequently
um and to a layman audience it's not
clear exactly what it means. So what
what is opponent processing and how does
it help shed light on this complex
problem?
Sure. Um and maybe along the way I can
point out how relevance realization
really gives some specific teeth to
claims of embodiment from four cogs. Uh
because I I'd like the point you made
and maybe we we don't have to do it
right now but I'd like to come back to
it. how relevance realization is kind of
a glue that glues together predictive
processing and for ecogi in powerful way
and makes them all including itself
mutually stronger from that integration
uh but yeah the opponent processing so
let's just note something at many
different levels of analysis in your
biology you will find opponent
processing at work I'll take one that's
very easy to explain and people have a
ready experience of it uh so we are all
constant stantly, mostly unconsciously,
although it's affected by conscious
factors. We're constantly recalibrating
and adjusting, I dare I say it, we're
even evolving our level of metabolic
arousal. I don't mean just sexual
arousal. Don't be Freud here. I mean
arousal. How much how much how how sort
of activated are you? How sort of
energized are you? Um, and the problem
is there isn't there isn't some state
you homeostatic state you're looking for
with that because if there's a tiger in
the room, I need to go to maximal right
arousal. Uh, uh, and if I'm going to
sleep, I need to go to minimal arousal
and I can't just be sort of Canadian and
keep sort of average arousal at all
times because then I don't fall asleep
and I get killed by tigers. And so it
constantly has to be like we're talking
about has to constantly readjusting. So
what what has evolved in your biology is
your autonomic meaning self-governing.
It's a self-organizing system like you
said it's a dynamical entity. Your
autonomic nervous system and what it
does is it couples together two
subsystems
that are have opposite biases from each
other. Your So your sympathetic system
is biased to I I'll speak
anthropomorphically just because it
speeds things up. Your sympathetic
system is biased to seeing as much of it
can of the world as threat or
opportunity and arousing you as much as
it can. And your parasympathetic system
is biased the opposite way. It's biased
to seeing as much of the world as
secure, safe, a place where you can rest
and recover. And then these subsystems
are not independent from each other.
They're locked together and they're they
are als they're continually trying to
shut each other off
and they're constantly competing that
way. But they're cooperatively
competing. It's not adversarial. They're
cooperatively competing. And what
happens is the constant tradeoff between
those proc between those processes
constantly right in very dynamic manner
constantly recalibrates your level of
arousal to the world. And that's
opponent processing. And what you find
is you got that you know there's other
there's opponent processing between your
focal vision and your peripheral vision.
there's opponent processing plausibly
between your left and right hemispheres.
The number of these things like u uh is
huge and I say at many different levels
of analysis. Um and so um I think a
point of processing is a clue uh to how
relevance realization is actually
undertaken by your embodied uh
cognition.
Wonderful. And immediately to anyone
interested in active inference or um its
manifestation in continuous state spaces
as predictive processing it what we'll
be screaming out is this notion of an
attractor set or our homeostatic
equilibrium which Carl has spoken about
at length obviously and and as has many
other researchers but this idea that
what this we are we suffer um but we
also uh embody in a kind of positive way
this itinerancy. We we never we're never
stuck in a single um mode. We we are
endowed with the capacity to go beyond
our homeostasis and return back to it,
but we're always in a sense being drawn
without ever residing with without ever
having stopped at that homeostatic set
point. Um so let's now fold in active
inference to the picture. what does it
provide relevance realization
um and the formulation of relevance
realization that couldn't be done purely
with fore cognitive science.
So I mean I'm going to talk about it in
terms of predictive processing because
that's the one that's the formulation of
it that lines up most cleanly uh with
the theoretical integration. uh as you
said there's there's clear derivation
relations between active inference and
predictive processing and also between
them and the basian uh math but the
basian math if we were to actually
strictly apply it would be
computationally intractable so we're
doing some approximation function so I'm
just going to take it that everybody
sort of knows that I'm playing fair with
this right I'm not I'm not trying to be
dodgy here um and so um relevance
realization is grounded in uh the idea
of problem solving And problem solving
actually assumes a fundamental thing
which again is so obvious to us which is
the state you're in and the state you
want to be in are not the same state.
That's the defining feature of a
problem. If I'm in a state I want to be
in I want to be sitting in this chair. I
am I don't have a problem. U right and
now what that means is you're all you're
you're immediately into something very
interesting. The organism is trying to
actually predict a possible state in the
world and prepare itself alter. So it's
an agent. It doesn't just behave. It
alters its behavior to alter the con the
states in the world. Right? And so it is
trying to I would say predictively
prepare for the world. is trying to
predict the world but prepare itself for
that world but also prepare the world so
it's more likely to come out in the
prediction that it seeks right and so I
I put those two together um and I I talk
about anticipation
um and so you're whenever you're problem
solving you're anticipating a goal
meeting that prediction and preparation
now for econ doesn't directly talk about
that as as clear as it needs to it talks
about coupling
and it talks about affordances and I
think there's a deep connection between
opponent processing optimal gripping and
affordances and maybe we can explore
that at some point uh but typically one
of the things where uh for cogsai has
some challenges is in more distal
relations uh to the environment because
it tends to rely primarily on coupling
and you know this is a long-standing
critique that one of my colleagues Brian
Kentwell Smith at the University of
Toronto because that is where all
knowledge is flowing from um right uh
has made he said you know uh you can be
predictively coupled to things that
you're in direct causal contact with but
you know uh um uh sorry dynamically
coupled not predictively coupled my my
apologies uh but you how do you do
things that are much more distal and for
me that that is key and here's why there
I think in I think when we evaluate even
intuitively
um so I'm using that as an authority and
just showing how readily this works for
us. Um, when we evaluate an organism for
its intelligence, we tend to it in two
interlocking ways. We do it in terms of
I think how how well does it zero in on
relevant information. How well does it
pay attention to what it needs? We look
at an animal. We go, "Wow, that's really
good." Notice how it's noting subtle
differences. But we also evaluate the
intelligence of an organism. And Michael
Leven talks about this with this
cognitive light cone idea is how deeply
into the world they can anticipate. And
I don't mean just spatial temporally. I
also mean it modally possibility like
when I talk to my cat and I say you know
you know where's your toy? The cat looks
at me and I go oh well right I say to my
puppy where's your ball? And she goes
into the other room looks for the ball
finds it under the couch and brings it
all the way back to me. I go wow you're
really smart. Right? And so we get this
because we we know how just moment by
moment that adaptive ability is built on
what how distally can we pursue goals.
We tend to evaluate people. Wow, you
pursued a long-term goal and you brought
it about. So that's what's missing and I
think that's what's really afforded. Now
I want to make one more point and then
I'll I'll shut up so you can you can ask
me another question which is these two
issues anticipating more deeply and
remember I don't just mean spatial
temporally I mean modally and relevance
realization are deeply interconnected
the more you anticipate the more the
problem of relevance realization goes up
exponentially and so these two things
right they I I would argue because
they're interlocking they have to be
solved together and I think that's why
we use both of them as evaluations of
the intelligence of an organism.
Okay, I'd like to backtrack to that
second argument
after this after what I say here. It um
yeah, it it strikes me that what
predictive processing can give perhaps
where fore cognitive science doesn't but
I'm happy to be schooled on this. Um,
and I know Varela and autoparesis in
some sense pre-eshadowed um, and
prefigured what I'm about to say is that
it kind of gives a ground to our action
and to our perception which is that we
have to have a model of the world and a
model of ourselves which is not only
descriptively viable but also
normatively viable.
Yes. in so in so far as it's all like
it's very important for me to be able to
predict the world but as you said we
aren't just at the behest of the world's
dynamics we can change the world
according to our preferences
exactly
and I think what predictive processing
gives us is although I although to be
fair I think Carl might say that this is
a bit of an overshoot is a is a telos
is a fundamental attractor set to which
our perception and action is is governed
So I think that's kind of the way that I
see the the added benefit of this
convergence between um predictive
processing and um relevance realization.
What I was also going to say there is
that it's fantastic that you're
mentioning this kind of deep temporal
modeling because for my eyes that's
really where a lot of the the work is
being done right now which is that
selfhood consciousness even perhaps
space itself is downstream on the fact
that we can downstream on the degree to
which we can model the slower dynamics
and the faster dynamics in a generative
hierarchy. So that's
I think that's I I'm in complete
agreement with that. I think that's an
extension of the argument I made. Uh
yeah.
And so what I wanted to pick up there is
you said if I heard correctly that the
more the deeper your temporal model, the
more you can model slower fluctuations
in the environment, the more critical
relevance realization becomes, the
higher the stakes in some sense.
Yes. Yes. Very much. I'm interested in
unpicking that argument because for my
eyes there there are plenty of things
out there that don't have deep temporal
models. So um I don't a virus for
example just be reacting to very uh
coarse grain features of the
environment. But for them relevance
realization at least to my eyes appears
as critical as it would for a human.
It it is it is and and so I think it's
how how can I put it? I think it's
always a demanding problem. I'm so I'm
not I'm not denying that even uh the uh
the parramium uh has to uh do salience
landscaping. It has to I'm going to use
a word very neutally here. I'm not
conoting anything about consciousness,
but it has to recognize this molecule as
food and that molecule as poison and
swim reliably towards the one and away
from the other. I'm not I so I think the
problem is always there as I was trying
to indicate as soon as you have problems
as soon as your goal states are distinct
and I think the space opens up very
quickly exponentially I just meant that
it exponentially gets worse
right this
this is why you see u across species
hyperbolic discounting temporal
discounting because that's a that's a
huge relevance realization machine is
about salience discounting right and the
point of that is is Because as you open
into the future, the number of
possibilities goes up exponentially. And
so you need to have this attenuation
function. So you don't get overwhelmed
by the possibilities as you extend your
cognition into the future. That's why we
have hyperbolic discounting. And we pay
a huge price for it. It makes us
procrastinate. It makes us difficult to
give up to pursue our long-term goals.
So there's even a trade-off relationship
in there, but I won't get into it. But
that's an example. There's a good reason
why we must have something like temporal
discounting across species. That's what
Angley showed is because the relevance
realization issue just it gets even
worse. It starts out bad and gets even
worse.
Right. Wonderful. And yeah, I mean a lot
of your work we we'll come to
affordances now because a lot of your
work is centered on the notion of
affordances.
So affordances are the possibilities for
action afforded actually that's circular
possibilities for action granted by the
environment. I afforded was a verb and
then Gibson made it now.
Um,
how much has the predictive processing
framework supplemented your
understanding of affordances and perhaps
the way that what we perceive in the
world is not necessarily a feature list
of objects.
Yeah.
But um they are fundamentally
affordances. I see my glass of water as
griable rather than being glass this
dimension. And I only asked that because
as I said as as conscious animate
cognizers we are blessed with the
capacity to change the world in
accordance with our priors which makes
action really the fundamental currency
for autopoesis for self-organization. So
does it has predictive processing ramped
up the uh importance that you give to
Gibsonian affordances? Um I don't know
if it ramped up because I I always
thought uh I I had literally learned
this stuff from John Kennedy uh Leonard
Gibson's greatest prote
uh impressed by this um and it it
occurred to me that relevance
realization
um the realization of relevance and I
mean realization in both senses
actualizing a possibility and becoming
aware of it or at least detecting it in
some fashion. um that it's a
prototypical kind of affordance. The
thing about affordances is they're not
found in the object or in the organism.
The griability of the glass is not in
the glass. Can't be gripped by a
parramium and it's not in my uh you know
in my hand. My hand can't grasp Africa
or the sun, right? It's in it's in a
fitted relation between them. And that's
exactly what relevance is. It's a fitted
relationship between. So I always before
I I came into a a deep dialogue with
predictive processing I already saw a
deep relationship between relevance
realization and affordances and I think
um part of my work has been to really
explore the deep ontological
significance of that that we have a
category that sort of falls outside this
was Gibson's intent too
this is what for Cogai is really talking
about falls outside our our our belief
that we have a complete exhaustive
dichotomy between the subject objective
and the objective between the inner
world and the outer world. And so
there's this other important I call it
the transjective this betweenness this
connectedness that you see in adaptivity
you see in relevance but you also see it
like you said now what what do I think
the predictive processing did I I I it's
allow me I want to talk just I want to
talk back and forth symmetrical not just
linear so I think what the predictive
processing does is emphasize the need to
try and explain rather than just
I don't want to be cruel, so I'm being a
little bit oversimplistic. I'm doing
that just for speed.
Sure.
But generally it it's like
Yeah, but how do the affordances get
actualized in the fore column? Like
there's a lot of affordances all the
time. And what I'm interested is when
how do those affordances become well
salient and obvious to me? So they
become binding on my sensory motor
behavior and and that was always
something of uh you know not that you
know there's Redfield and others who
were doing some work on it but typically
they start to invoke predictive
processing to try and explain that
mechanism of like okay there's a there's
a huge affordance network but I'm not
like how do I here we go again how do I
select and actualize the ones that I'm
actually going to that actually go into
my salience landscaping and I think
predictive processing especially with
the notion of precision waiting does a
good job of that and what I think
relevance realization helps to do to
predictive processing a bunch of other
things but one thing is
predictive processing basically there's
subtlety to this and I know there's lots
of math but just to keep going right
that you know well what attention is is
the precision waiting it's this meta
function and I think that's a very good
argument but there but there's a
conceptual analysis that's been needed
but it's like but what is salience and
one of the arguments I can make is well
what the precision waiting is doing is
relevance realization and relevance
realization uh when relevance
realization re does a higher order
finding relevant of an affordance that
has been generated by lower order
relevance realization that's when
something becomes salient to us and so
we can actually give a conceptual
explanation that goes with the
theoretical identity claim in predictive
processing that precision waiting is
attention and what it gives you is
salience. So they can they can unpack
each other. I think what another thing
that happens is
relevance realization is deeply
connected to for ecoside because
relevance is grounded I would argue in
autopoesis.
Um relevance relevance is always
relevant to an organism right and so
that means relevance realization isn't
cold calculation. It's how the organism
cares about some information rather than
all the other information because it is
constantly taking care of itself. There
are literally and I mean this physically
things that matter to it and things that
it must import into itself important
things and some of that's also
information. And so why that if you if
you can if if you can glue for ecog sign
predictive processing together I think
you can answer some of the questions
maybe even challenges that some people
in for ecogi are making of predictive
processing and saying well it's not
really connected to embodiment. I think
no no if you show a deep theoret
theoretical integration of predictive
processing and relevance realization and
then relevance realization and autoesis
then you've really strongly glued
predictive processing and 40 cogsai
together. So that's some of the thing
that's some of the important theoretical
work that can be done. Yeah, absolutely.
I I would love to jump into um the
critiques that certain fore um cognitive
research uh cognition researchers have
leveraged at predictive processing. But
let's um let's leave that for a second.
This is exactly what I was talking about
in terms of Telos. Um, which is that
exactly this this notion of care and and
when I spoke to Ma Alarasan, an active
inference researcher um last week, we
kind of actually ended up concluding
this is almost a hyaggarian sense of
care that on our existence.
Can I can I just interrupt there? Yeah.
Right. A hideigarian sense of care was
exactly what I was in invoking and I
Right. And I was deeply influenced by
Drifus and the frame problem. We got
this from H Highaidiger. Right. So the
the connection you just drew is very I I
that yeah I I explicitly argue for that.
Excellent. So yeah, I mean I personally
think um that the Haidig Hygarian Drafus
Merlo Ponty lineage needs to be
integrated more into
Yes.
active inference and I'm speaking to Dr.
Marilyn Standera who has done work on
Haidiger and autopes. So that will be
really that will be really fun in the
upcoming weeks. This is exactly what I
was talking about in terms of telos
which is that taking a stance on your
own existence can be computationally
modeled as having these kind of high
precision prior.
So our homeostatic set point will be
different from a snakes and that
actually gives a really solid
explanation of why we act differently in
certain context than snakes. Um and so
that was my kind but then that said I
will have to make clear that Carl
is himself although he has spoken about
existential imperative says that there
actually is no imperative all that
you're really saying is if a thing like
us is to persist over time this is what
it needs to do and it's just a it's just
cast as a minimization of free energy.
So, I think there's an interesting
question there that maybe you could have
a go at, which is to what degree do you
see this as a genuine imperative um
versus just what things do to
self-organize over time?
Yeah. And so, I mean, and and uh Carl's
no slouch, so he's welcome. I I I
sometimes don't like it when people who,
you know, are physicists or something
start commenting on philosophical uh
normative questions uh with an authority
they don't properly possess. Uh but I
know I mean Carl's a great theorist and
um and I know he's philosophically
educated. Um I have not yet to talk to
him, but I hope I do get to do so.
You can do it here.
So, um,
yeah, I mean, so I'm going to argue
later if I get a chance that what
relevance realization doing is strongly
analogous,
uh, obviously a very different time
scale uh to what evolution does about
constantly uh uh redesigning the adapted
fittedness of the of organisms to the
environment and allowing organisms to
fit their environments to them because
as you keep emphasizing and I keep
agreeing with, it's not passive. It's
not right. The organism is shaping the
environment as the environment is
shaping the organism. Niche construction
and all that sort of thing. Um, and I
think that's all right. And I and there
again that's a very clear connection to
for eoxide again. But this deeper
question I do want to do it. I want to
pause and I want to slow down because it
it is a really important question uh
because it gets us beyond what we might
call scientific explanations of how and
into properly but not useless
philosophical reflection of sort of why
and why does this matter to me because
as you've mentioned
I'm deeply concerned with you know
issues of meaning in life this this this
largely metaphorical ical nebulous
notion that humans seek meaningful
lives, lives that are worth living even
given all of our failures and our faults
and our flaws and our foolishness and
our frustration, right? And pretty clear
empirical evidence that it's not
reducible uh to just subjective
well-being or pleasure and pretty good
conceptual philosophical argument
because it's that's where it's relevant
that it's not reducible to just living a
moral existence. You could live a very
moral existence in which you're sort of
experiencing the pleasure of food and
other things. Um and and and you know
certain stability in your environment,
but you can be very very lonely. You
could be very lonely. So and what what
that loneliness points to I'm just
making an intuitive gesture. That's not
a tight argument. I have tight
arguments, but the the gesture is people
are seeking a kind of connectedness. And
now you see where I'm getting to
relevance realization and what we're
talking about this niche construction
the fittedness the belonging
togetherness this mutually shaping like
this is this I argue that that's exactly
the connectedness human beings are
they're seeking the meaning in life now
you can then ask the question and people
and I'm going to play with two terms of
phrase here to play with that I think we
clearly seek meaning in life
uh and I think the evidence for that is
growing And it it converges with the
psychological work on meaning in life
and on what Karen Allen calls
belongingness. If you don't feel that
you belong, you're in trouble. And
you're in trouble across all these
measures, cognitive, emotional, social,
financial block. Like you're in trouble.
Physiologically, you're in trouble. Um
that's why solitary confinement is such
a punishment, right?
Um so
is there a meaning of life to the
meaning in life?
The meaning of life is that is there
some sort of cosmic
destiny, cosmic order to which we are
ultim which we are ultimately trying to
find.
And here's the thing, I don't think I
have enough evidence for that.
I think that there's lots of evidence
for meaning in life. And if I'm right
that it's relevance realization and if
that's something very much like
evolution, right? Evolution is
constantly redesigning adaptivity,
but there isn't a final thing that
evolution is aiming towards. There isn't
a final form of life. There isn't some
like what we're doing is like the
sculptor. We're constantly refining and
then finally one day we will have the
final form of life. And um I think this
is fundamentally flawed and I think this
matters philosophically. I don't think
previous forms of life were in some in
in any kind of moral sense superior to
us. So I don't believe in any nostalges
and we just have to get back there.
Nope. And I don't believe the utopia. We
are working towards the final ultimate
thing that we'll all agree for all time
is the most relevant most salient. I I
don't believe that's how this works. So
I reject nostalg
utopias. The idea that there's a t- loss
can either mean there's a t- loss to
meaning in life which is it's like Carl
says it's necessary it's constitutive
necessary for living things to have
this. But does that mean there's any
metaphysical necessity to there being
living things? That's a different
question. Now, here's my weak answer at
that one. Sorry, long question, but you
asked like this is like almost up there
with like God question, right?
Right.
I note that I'm in a very difficult
situation. I can't see any evidence for
and I'm not attacking God here. As you
know, I'm very respectful and even
appreciative of of religious frameworks
and religious lives, but I can't see any
evidence for that. However, if you were
to ask me which is a better universe,
one with life in it and one without life
in it, even if you couldn't exist in
either one, I would say the one with
life in it. There's some primordial
judgment going on there um that has some
kind of metaphysical import. Now, it's
weak. I I I admitted that ahead of time.
And so I'm giving you a very I'm sorry
very long but wishy-washy answer. I
don't really think I believe in anything
like the meaning of life. But I do think
there's a metaphysical import to being
connected to reality. We find reality
being connected to reality inherently
valuable for its own sake. and we find
worlds in which things can realize
reality, better worlds than ones that
don't have that in it. That's my answer.
No, it's a wonderful answer and it um
it's really helped me and hopefully our
audience clarify exactly what I mean by
an existential imperative, which is that
the free energy principle doesn't tell
you what you're here for.
No,
it tells you if you're here, what are
you doing? like [laughter]
and given your phenotype um and given
your culture and etc etc. So that's a
really useful um
sort of explanation of exactly what I
was going for there. Um, and actually it
points to something I said to Carl right
at the end of our podcast, which at time
of recording this came out yesterday. So
people should definitely check it out
because he's
sure for sure
he's on top form, which is that I asked
him I I
mentioned Thomas Nagel. So Thomas Nagel
has this kind of very romantic
philosophical notion that life is death
is bad because life is fundamentally
good. And it points to kind of your
thought experiment. If we had two
worlds, one with life and one without
life, I think we would all intuitives
intuitively say the one with life is
better. Whether that has any
metaphysical import as you say is is up
for grabs. I was going to I'm going to
ask sort of um jumping on the back of
the initial thing you said which was
about connectedness um and
belongingness. So if we take this from a
theoretical or computational stance in
active inference, what this looks like
to me is we embody a model of the world
which um we can so we can make
fundamentally sound predictions about
how the world will unfold and how about
we will and how we will act to make that
world more compatible with our
preferences. Now when that was
formalized initially in the active
inference literature
immediately a response to this came in
the form of what's called the dark room
problem. So this is sort of papers in
2011 2012 and and they've been rebuted
in multiple ways but the basic idea is
why don't humans just seek out dark
rooms where maybe they have access to
food and water but they don't really
seek out but in a state where they don't
go and explore and they're not curious
because what you're seeing there is
actually a perfect coupling between your
predictions of the world and the well
and the way the world is unfolding to
your eyes. So I was wondering whether
you had pondered the dark room problem
and where you see exploration
and epistemic affordances coming into
play here.
Yeah, I think that the dark room problem
I'm not I I I I'm happy with all the
other rebuttals. Um and I don't and I
don't know I don't know I don't know
them all so I may be stepping on
somebody else's toes. So if I am whoever
you are I apologize. Yeah. Um I think
this is a you know a lock in
individualist model of cognition and how
we work and I think it is therefore the
presupposition well is that no um that's
actually I don't agree with that
presupposition that our cognition is
fundamentally individualistic in that
way I think we are you know we are
social socioultural mammals and let me
point to one thing you So yes, measures
of G are very robustly predictive. But
you know what's also really pred a very
powerful way of predicting your
behavior? Your attachment style.
This is also very robust. Now that that
means think about what that actually
means and this you know and this goes
into the heart of religious traditions
like agopic love right when you have a
child you have to invert your relevance
arrow. It's not how that being is
relevant to you. You invert everything
around. This is agopic love and it's how
it's different from erotic love or
phileia love. You you invert everything
around, right? And so that it's how am I
relevant to this being? How am I
relevant to this being? And how can I be
relevant in a way that turns it into a
person? Turns it into an intelligent,
rational, self-reflective relevance
realizer, predictive processor, meaning
maker. Right? And so, well, I first of
all, where are my attachment
relationships in the dark room? Well,
there's other people in the dark room.
Soon as there's other people in the dark
room, all the problems that you thought
you got away from by putting me in a
dark room return. Other people have
different goals than me. They have
different needs. They're going to move
around differently, right? That we're
going to have to decide about when and
where and how we gain access. Blah blah
blah blah blah. All of that immediately
unfolds. Secondly, and this is part of
fore COGS, I think the evidence for
extended cognition, distributed
cognition, that we evolve to to work in
groups and the collective intelligence
of that is actually our superpower. And
other people are making this argument.
Um I think that's clear. You standard
thing take the waste and selection task
put it an individual person highly
educated highly intelligent secondyear
you know psychology in a top tier
university from the 1960s on you put
them in the waste and selection task and
only 10% get it right right you replace
that same task with four people who are
allowed to talk to each other and the
success rate goes from 10% to 82%
reliably why because we do opponent
processing between each I do.
All right.
You have biases different from mine. And
if we work in opponent processing, not
adversarial, but if I say you're
probably a good source for correcting my
bias and I'm probably a good source for
correcting yours, we get the best
dynamical self-correction possible. And
so when you add in the fact of the
reality and there's actually evidence
empirical and formal for the power of
collective intelligence, the reality of
attachment, well then the dark room,
right, becomes filled with other people
who are trying to, you know, band
together to solve problems that they
can't solve individually. And then to
me, everything that the dark room
thought it had as an absurd like a
reductio absurdum disappears. That would
be my response.
Yeah. I think eventually the dark room
just becomes the world once you start
adding the things you need. Eventually,
you know, eventually it becomes a
civilization. Yeah, I love I love all
this stuff on distributed cognition. I
spent the first um six months of this
year working at UCL on um experiment
finding experimental ground for what's
called social baseline theory. Social
baseline theory is this idea that humans
like to study a human being in a lab by
itself is to study a human being at
deficit. A human being actually want its
physiological arousal to take one um one
factor
is at its baseline when it's with other
people and it will fluctuate according
to stuff like attachment style or the
relationship that one has with that
person which is really beautiful but
inverts our kind of well maybe not
common sense but our inst
institutionalized notion of what it is
to be a person which is kind of
alone. Yeah. Wonderful. Well, I'm going
to take this argument a little bit
further if if you let me. um because
this is something that we spoke about a
couple of months ago and I think Mark
might have a different opinion so it' be
cool to sort of unpick all the
I have this um slightly fuzzy
wishy-washy idea that the notion that
okay so I I always think about a climber
climbing a rock face or a climbing wall
and the climbing wall is a kind of
beautiful canonical example of an
affordance-based landscape. It's rich
full of affordances. It's got the toe
holds, the finger holds. So in many ways
what the um rock in terms of active
inference what it allows the rock
climber to do is to self-evidence um or
or find evidence for its own model about
itself as um a successful rock climber.
Yeah.
Now that's relatively well established
in the literature. What isn't
established is my kind of again slightly
wishy-washy idea which is that the rock
climber is offering affordances to the
wall. And so this this is why I about
you know right at the beginning of our
conversation I spoke about mutual
coupling. So what dynamical systems
theory gives us what um autoparoesis
gives us what active inference gives us
is this idea that um to exist is not to
be this kind of rayified self that um
takes a objective stance on the world
and actually what it is is this really
the fundamental unit of analysis should
be this dynamic mutual coupling between
agent and arena to use your terminology.
Yeah. Do you think it's an over I mean
I've spoken to Mark about this and he he
uses he he says it's something like an
overextension of the term affordances to
say that the human being is offering
affordances to the climbing wall. I know
Mark isn't here to defend himself. So
again I'm not going to put one
but and I will definitely raise this
with him again but just for your own
ears how does that argument sound to
you?
I like the argument and yeah I don't
want to speak guild of Mark. I'll only
speak to the propositions that you spoke
on his behalf. And [snorts] I'm very
happy to I I mean Mark and I work close
together. Mark is one of the best people
I know. Mark's a former student of mine.
I'm very proud of Mark. So um uh but um
I actually agree with you. Now that goes
to another connection I make in my work
that would probably be a little bit
stranger to the ears of many of your
listeners. They might say, "Oh, I get
the why he wants to connect uh, you
know, predictive processing to relevance
realization and the four eco side." But
now what you're doing and this is where
I do a lot of my what I call my deeper
ontological work and this is where the
hideagarian stuff really comes to bear
is this is all the work I do on on
neoplatanism which may sound like
something very arcane but it again um
here's here's the proposal that once we
really profoundly accept affordances and
once we accept that they are
reciprocally realizing I agree with you
the affordance not only discloses things
about me it discloses things about the
world and that's a way in which things
like Haidiger's notion of truth as altha
as the a as an event as the disclosure
rather than a static property of our
propositions um I think that bang on now
as filler argues and I've been arguing
for a while and John Rousen uh filler's
book is called uh neoplatanism haidiger
and the history of being relation is
ontological ground that relationality is
actually the the ultimate nature of
reality um Haidiger's is actually
turning back towards this because what
does that give you? If you've had if you
have that and I think this is a fair way
to put it if you have that alathetic
notion of affordance then you are
getting back to the neoplatonic theory
of knowing by conformity knowing by
participation and the deeper argument
goes something like this um that if the
fundamental grammar of your cognition I
don't mean the content your content can
go all wrong and all but if the
fundamental grammar the bottom up top
down all all this stuff we're talking
about if it's not picking up on
something fundamental about how reality
is structured, right? Then you face a
kind of profound solopism, a profound
kind of skepticism. Um, and I think that
is ultimately leads you into all kinds
of performative contradictions that I
and I agree with Whitehead there as
devastating as propositional
contradiction. There's a longer argument
there and I can point to please check
out some of my talks on on YouTube about
this longer argument like Pixtock's uh
aspects of truth which he said you know
all the things we use to dichomize this
right we had the analytic synthetic
distinction that is broken down under
philosophical criticism uh we had the
theory fact distinction that is broken
down we is we had the the right the is
ought that has broken down like think
about is relevance in is or not well
blah right it's sort of both. Right.
Right. And so her point is all the
things that were used to cleave and then
what we tried to do is we tried to make
the logical world the thing that sort of
stuck the two worlds together and that
collapsed under God and other people.
And so we're back to the idea that we
either we either we either go into the
lock in cabinet in which we're locked
inside of our heads. We're somehow
getting postcards sent to us. we think
they might be from an outside world that
we think might be out there and we're
trying to build it from the postcards
and we're doomed. That's never going to
get us there. And so I think if you have
an alothetic notion of affordance, you
start to make the argument that how
reality is realizing and how we are
doing relevance realization are
fundamentally participating in the same
principles in a profound way. Um and uh
and I think yeah that I I'm I I have no
doubt that my Mark might not not uh want
to do this. I think Mark would be I
would agree with Mark that this is not a
direct derivation from sort of classic
Fristonian presentations of active
inference and predictive processing
basian brain we should settle on a name.
Uh but uh um but I think if you make the
connections through deeper into Gibson,
deeper into Fory Cogai, deeper into
Haidiger, you get back to this notion
that with the prevalent notion of
knowing that when we know something,
what we're doing is
our structural functional organization
is identifying with the structural
functional organization of the thing and
we are we are both participating in that
same form, that same principle, that
same grammar and that has all kinds of
metaphysical and ontological
consequences, even uh ethical
consequences. It means talking about the
true, the good and the beautiful becomes
something very relevant again.
Yeah. Yeah. No, this is this is exactly
where I wanted to go and exactly aligns
with with the way I'm thinking about the
free energy principle at the moment,
which is I have a skepticism between the
internal and the external distinction.
Yes. And this is something I spoke about
with K. So a a classic problem when one
starts reading active inference as I
spoke about with Carl is whether one
would consider the um the agent or the
um internal dynamics as having having a
model of the external world or
instantiating a model of the external
world model.
Excellent. Excellent.
And this comes back to sort of um cyber
cybernetic formulations what it is to be
a good regulator. So Colin Ashby and and
and all of that stuff from the 50s and
60s. So I have an inherent skepticism
because I would I kind of take the
stance that actually all that the
external dynamics are doing is
instantiating a particularized form of
the external dynamics. And this is very
easy once you take out the picture of a
hunculized ego. Just if you look at it
in terms of just a particle physics,
we're just a instantiation of some um of
the the physics that defines everything
else. But we just we just actually seem
to have a kind of complexified markoff
blanket on Markov blanket form of that.
But there's nothing particularly
distinct about that. And we'll come to
consciousness because
maybe there is um and that's I guess is
the big elephant in the room here. But
it's funny that you mentioned Haidiga
because Haidiga to my to my eyes and in
my opinion and then obviously Drafus and
Merlo Ponty and and the phenomenologist
followed Haidiga
really um he's the one who strikes at
this um established distinction between
a subject and an object.
Yes.
So the carteesian distinction and and
then this is where his kind of gripes
with Satra came in. Now
my question is is that yes if you read H
highaidigga Darzine the ground of Darine
is this kind of interreationality alfair
is the disclosure of truth in an inter
interreational
relationship so to speak
but there still seems to be some kind of
subject who um you know the the hammerer
who is hammering away at the nail. Now
from the perspective of the hammerer,
he's not some raified ego who is
objectifying the nail. That all that is
really being witnessed there from the
level of consciousness is the disclosure
of activity.
But still we can give a description of a
hammer and a nail. So to what degree in
your thinking do you completely
eradicate the subject object
distinction? Um, and is there anything
that you think predictive processing has
to say about that?
I think uh well oh the second question
wasn't
don't worry about don't worry about
second question [laughter]
don't worry about
I'm happy to think about it with you uh
I have put a lot of thought into the
first question.
Yeah. Um, and so I mean I think Filler
is right in his book that our subjective
objective divide is our version of the
appearance reality distinction and and
it's just our version in the ancient
world they had a different version. So
ours is an in-out metaphor. How is the
inner and the outer connected? Um, and
the ancient world is the problem of the
one and the many. How is the lower and
the upper connected? and and it and and
what what and once you see that you
realize that there's a deeper structural
problem that isn't bound to the inner
outer or the uh the emergence and the
emanation it's it's this connectivity
issue and what what FER argues and
there's a lot of other people uh
convergent on this is like if you try to
if you if you go with an arisatilian
metaphysics that what's most real are
substances in the Arisatilian sense
which things that can independently
exist. Um then this becomes a deep
problem for you and that kind of
ontology I would argue and I can make
the argument drives you towards a
nominalistic um epistemology. Um and
then you get you know AAM's version of
it or Kant's version of it where all of
the patterns and all the information are
just in the mind which means the mind is
radically other because it is the only
place that information intelligibility
actually exists and the world is
profoundly ab absurd in a deep deep way
and I think that leads you into uh well
first of all it makes science impossible
and it leads you into all kinds of
existential potential and moral
dilemmas. And if you then take a look at
the logic of trying to get you can't
actually and this is what filler does
very carefully, you can't actually get
relations out of properties that belong
to the relata. The relations have to
precede the rata in a very important
way. So I think there's a deep at a very
deep level I do want to call it into
question. I do want to challenge that uh
that go first of all we it's historical
it's cultural we we pretend as if that
is the only way in which human beings
have related to the world like I said
even in the west that's not their
problem in the ancient world their
problem is the problem of the one and
the many it's not the problem of the end
now what does this all ground in I think
this grounds in the common problem of
the relationship between appearance and
reality and here's where I can now say
something that aligns with my previous
argument about relationality.
See, so and I'm going to borrow a term
from uh raor here, the hermeneutics of
suspicion. The hermenics of suspicion is
that appear and we've got it because of
Freud and Nichi and blah blah blah.
There's historical reasons and those are
valuable critiques by the way, but the
hermenics of suspicion says appearances
are distorting. They're deceptive.
They're distractive, right? They're
disruptive. And what we should do is
always question whether or not they are
leading us into reality.
Now Marl Ponty has a great argument
against that that he gets from I maybe
he doesn't get but it's it's in Plato
which is wait you're treating real like
red like you could just say you can look
at an isolated thing and say that's real
but real is a comparative term. So of
course is illusion. To say this is an
illusion is to say this is an illusion
in comparison in relation to something
that is more real and that thing is in
relation so on and so forth. Right? And
what that means is first of all you have
to see that those judgments are
inherently relational and secondly you
have to call into question the her the
the independence of the hermeneutics of
suspicion. The hermenetics of suspicion
is actually parasitic on the
hermeneutics of beauty there, right? It
depends on there being things that we
agree on by saying that's where
appearance discloses
reality rather than distorting it.
Right? And then as soon as you do that,
that undercuts the deep divide because
you ultimately make these divisions
between the one and the many or the
subject and the object by getting a
hermeneutics of suspicion into the
appearance reality distinction. That's
at least the argument I would make.
Interesting. Yeah, I I like the I like
the suspicion of binariness
uh inherent in all of this. Um it it it
speaks to me and I think it speaks to
people who are interested in active
inference and the notion of sort of
philosophical vagueness as well.
Um at what point is something real is is
fundamentally a comparative term in the
web of things that could be considered
real.
Um
yeah,
that that right.
Yeah. I I I'm I I'm trying to do this
without invoking a binary, but um you
mentioned earlier that 4E cognitive
scientists do have their critiques of
active inference um and and predictive
processing and I I will stick with
active inference actually for now and I
will explain [laughter] why later. Um
it's not that interesting. So this this
is people like Tony Camro or Ed Bags um
who who are radical inactivists and what
they're critiquing in a sense is an
internalist picture of active inference.
So, this is some, again, I'm not putting
words into people's mouths, but if you
read um Jakob Howi's um 2016 paper about
self-evidencing,
some of the language may to some people
imply that there is a homunculus that
has a representational picture of the
world. And this to the ears of a uh
inactivist is deeply worrying.
I would love to as a fore cognitive
scientist um with obviously a vested
interest in predictive processing as
well. I'd love to just hear your take on
that debate and um again without
striking at binaries and whether you
think those critiques are legitimate.
Well, I mean it depends what you mean by
legitimate. I mean, you know, there's
also the ones that Evan Thompson made
and I hold Evan very highly. Um, I mean
they're legitimate in that they are
they're they're wellmade arguments in
peer-reviewed journals and so we we have
no right to be dismissive of them. Well,
if I was to say if I was to say that
let's take as an axiom of active
inference like this is just um
this isn't the case but let's just say
for sake of argument that you have some
um internalist representations of a
statistical model right so you are in a
sense you're not just embodying a model
you actually have a model. So again it
comes back to that distinction we're
talking about. would a uh an activist
critique of that internalism be um be
justified?
Um
so the reason why I'm hesitating is this
is landing on the swamp of what do we
mean by representation?
uh which is I mean so
does the thermostat represent the
temperature in the environment and where
and everything I'm going to say is
controversial because of the swamp so I
want that understood please right I
would say no because what's needed is
right there there might be some coral
there there might be co-variation but uh
what I think the critiques of the
co-variation model of representation
locks ultimately model that what it did.
So we had the idea that representations
have to be similar to what they
represent. That's how they represent and
then you have all the problems with
similarity and Aristotle even could
bring that down. Um and then lock
replaced it with the co-variation model
to have a representation is I have
something in my head that reliably
co-varies with something in the world
and that's how it represents it. And
then the problem with the co-ariations
is they don't give you um the
specificity for example of thought
right. So this is covarying with a
bottle with a tool with a man-made
object like which is it those are not
the same things or not those are not the
same ideas but the this is covarying
causally with all of that and you have
you have the problem then of
aspectualization
and and the the lock answer of course is
we get we get aspects by doing
representation but I agree with Sorl
that that's the wrong way around that
any representation is inherently
aspectual. When I represent this as a
bottle, I'm only picking up on some of
its properties in so far as they are
relevant to each other in so far as they
are relevant to me. So representation
depends on aspectualization which
depends on relevance realization. And
this is not what you do with relevance
realization. You do not represent all
the facts, judge them to be irrelevant
and then zero in. So it's ultimately
nonrepresentational.
So what I would say is I I don't know
that at some level there's something
like representations
and but if if I agree with many
arguments that representations are more
than co-variation but there's this kind
of caridness and aspect caring and
aspectualization through them then they
depend on relevance realization which
grounds in autopolicis and is deeply
intertwined with predictive processing.
That would be my argu that would be my
response.
Splendid. And I guess I guess what
intuitively supports a more
representationless picture is
consciousness.
Um I think consciousness is become going
to become a recurring theme in this
podcast. Um
well it's the holy grail, right?
Is it is the holy grail. Um, and so I
guess my question here is is that if one
was to adopt a radically inactivist
view,
there's nothing in that picture which um
needs consciousness. So why couldn't my
mutual coupling with the world just
happen with the lights off? So this is
an argument I guess that's rooted in
Charmer's um 1995 paper which is you can
give me the function but you can't give
me the why. Why are the lights on?
And so I guess
In in other words, my question to you is
yes that we may have relevance
realization um preceding
perception or preced or or grounding
perception.
Yeah.
Then why do we have perception in the
first place?
So um again I'm going to give a gist of
an argument that I've spoken about at
length elsewhere and I'm trying to get
published on and presented at
conferences and so forth. So um I don't
think you can separate the function and
the nature questions which is what
charmer's hard problem uh relies on is
it? Yeah. Yeah. You've given me the
function but you've told me nothing
about the nature.
I don't think function works onlogically
like that. I think function has to be
plugged into the ontology and I think as
soon as we're talking about the ontology
of anything within a living organism,
we're talking about something
functional. So I think the questions
have to be answered interconnected. So
let's go let's go back. Let's say that
you give me
that um any cognitive agent has to be do
doing anticipatory relevance realization
or it's not going to be a general
problem solver. And then when it's doing
that, it has to be aspectualizing its
world. Right.
Right. It's it it's not react it's not
doing all of the all of this but this as
a bottle or the molecule as food. The
molecule. Right. And then if you then
start to pay attention to
let's look at the continuum of
consciousness.
Uh let's look at the possibility which I
have experienced. That's not even the
right sentence. Many people have and
this is Foreman's idea of something like
the pure consciousness event. And the
pure consciousness event doesn't have
well actually I need a distinction here.
I'm going to claim it doesn't have one
type of qualia but it has another type
of qualia in it. It doesn't have adject
there's no red there's no blue. There's
no cap. There's no dot there. Right.
You're not even conscious of
consciousness. You're just conscious.
Yeah.
Right. But what what it still has is it
still has the adverbial qualia. It still
has a sense of hearness
now. And the hearness is profound
presence. That's the language that's
used. The nowness, eternity, the the the
integration, right? The togetherness.
It's everything is one. So all the
adverbial qualia are still there and you
still have consciousness. That shows
that the adjectival qualia are not
necessary to consciousness. Now, I have
other arguments to show they're probably
not sufficient because if I give you
sort of atomic blips of blessness and
greenness and they're not bound together
and there's not a hearness and a nowness
so you can in any way orient them, I
don't think you have consciousness
either.
Right.
Um, so I'm not saying that adjectabio
qualia don't exist. I'm saying that
we've held consciousness hostage to
them. Yeah.
And what I'm proposing to you is that
what consciousness is doing is these
adverbial qualia which are just right
salience
which is just relevance realization
which is as far as we can tell tied to
the best evidence we have. It's all
controversial about the function of
consciousness. It's tied up with working
memory and attention which are both
doing higher order relevance
realization. We need to seem to need
consciousness for situations of
complexity, novelty or illdefinedness,
ones that are really demanding on
relevance realization. So you can make a
pretty and there's a lot of convergence
actually on what the function of
consciousness is relevance realization.
And I think if you plug in relevance
realization, you can at least get all
the adverbial qualia and that I think
gives you a lot of what consciousness
actually is.
Cool. Um, yeah, let's stay on adverbial
qualia because I I'd like to integrate
what you've just said with a more active
inference account of consciousness,
which there are and and they're they're
also diverse. But one well, I have to
ask a question before is does Foreman
um say that
so um feeling that this experience is
mine does he is is that one of his
verbal qualia that persists in the pure
consciousness event? So th that has
another thicket because the debate about
this is a raging debate. Evan Thompson
actually has a good anthology on this on
the self no self debate.
Right.
Right. And and
I think it's I think it's reasonable and
complies with most of the evidence,
which of course is self-report after the
fact, which is problematic, blah blah
blah blah. I agree with all of that. I'm
not dismissing that. But that's what we
basically have to go on right now. Um
that the ego narrative sense of mine and
me and I goes away. I
whether or not that is a complete loss
of
the self
as
as where relevance realization is
happening or something like that. Yeah.
um that that I'm not I'm not convinced
that that second thing is the case.
Okay.
I think so if you would allow me and
this is a torture distinction, a
distinction between the ego and the
self. I think these experiences very
much the ego goes away. I'm very
suspicious of the claim that the self
goes away because people are readily
able to recall these experiences. This
is what does report and I would report
to you and seamlessly integrate them
into their auto noetic autobiographical
memory. there isn't any weird disjarring
or where was I during that?
Yeah. [clears throat] Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. Excellent. The reason why I
asked that is because um a lot of
selfmodeling in active inference is
based on the work of Thomas Metzinger.
So Thomas Metinger is such a wonderful
addition to this conversation. So
I had a wonderful conversation with him
not that long ago.
Oh really? I love it.
On my channel amazing. I think he's I
think he's such an underrated and
important philosopher. Totally agree.
Yeah. Yeah. So he's got this notion of
so he makes a distinction between
phenomenal self-modeling and an
ontological self. So people intuitively
even everyone listening to this podcast
even the way we act on a day-to-day
basis is in lie of an ontological self.
So we can't help but really think of
ourselves as being this soul this
carteesian soul. But anyways invokes
this notion of phenomenal selfmodeling
how the system appears to itself. And
he's got this um minimal phenomenal self
which which has been unpicked in other
ways but he normally he speaks generally
of presentness mindness and
perspectleness.
Exactly what I've been talking about.
Yep. Exactly.
This gets fleshed out in some of the
acts of inference work. People like
Jakob Howy um Carl and Jakob Limonowski
have used um Metsinger's work for
several papers. And then on the other
end of that, we have what Carl turned an
epistemic agent model, which is the self
that
um the system that sees itself as
epistemic in the sense that it can
retrieve past memories to inform future
decisions and agentive in the fact that
it can conduct alostatic action, i.e. um
action to retain some homeostatic
equilibrium given what it knows about
the future. So me putting on a jumper
before I go outside because I know it's
going to be colder outside than it is
inside. The reason why I invoke the
minimal phenomenal selfhood is because
and Carl actually outlines this in the
podcast we did together that
consciousness may be downstream in a
sense on one a deep temporal model and
from that the sense of agency and he has
an argument from um referring to
dimensions um not in terms of sort of
millimeter size but in terms of um the
degree to which you have embedded
Markoff blankets.
um that when we're distant from our
actuators, what we end up doing is we
have to have a way of distinguishing
what's my action from what's your action
or from what the world how the world has
acted on us. And in doing that, we come
up with a self- other distinction, but
also the notion of an agentive self. The
idea that I can change the world in
accordance to my preferences as as I
mentioned beforehand. So to sort of
paraphrase Carl, what that seems to be
suggesting is that consciousness is
actually rooted in selfhood. And I know
there's this whole argument in Metinger
about whether that's the case.
That's why I asked whether mindness is
also part of these pure consciousness
events or whether it's kind of a posttop
inference. Just wondering whether you
had any ideas about that notion um and
whether we can truly have consciousness
without at least a sense of self.
Right. Okay. So um
uh let me try a few things. First of all
um I don't think it's inevitable that
human beings
model themselves as souls. I think
that's a western postcartisian
uh way of and that's even and and then
the soul as a
uh monatic single substance you can put
it that way uh you don't that's not even
the case in uh the ancient world of the
west certainly not the case in other
parts of the world etc. So I I I I
hesitate that that's um the claim that's
part of how the machinery must unfold.
Sure.
And then secondly, um I I worry about
saying, you know, that that that because
it isn't a soul, there isn't a self.
This is a weird notion of again of a
substance ontology being uh just
presupposed in an unquestioned manner. I
mean, look, we've discovered most things
aren't substances. This table, which
would be a classic aristatian substance,
is not a substance. It's it's a
dynamical system of atoms and quarks and
blah. And we don't go, "Oh, well,
because tables aren't substances, they
aren't real like that. We don't do
that." And so I like I I I I I just I I
want to just note that I'm worried that
there's a substance ontology creeping in
here and leading to certain conclusions.
Now that idea about uh uh this there's I
can't remember the name of the people uh
and I apologize for that.
There is a fairly recent theory of
consciousness that we're trying to
respond to all the libit experiments and
things like that. Um arguing that well
consciousness is sort of after the fact
but consciousness is actually for the
future.
Yeah.
Conscious. So the idea here is
consciousness is emerges out of the
evolution of episodic memory. So the
function of consciousness is to allow us
to create an episodic memory of
something we have already done. Uh right
and the point about the episodic memory
is soon as you get into episodic memory
you get into perspectival knowing.
That's what an episode is right. You
have a perspective right on a situation
what you found salient and relevant how
your actions and right in the arena
coupled or didn't couple the affect that
all of that all of that that's so bound
up with consciousness and and then they
and the point they make and I totally
agree with this is soon as you agree
that there are multiple kinds of knowing
not just propositional and procedural
but also perspectival and participatory
you get the argument that episodic
memory
affords
perspectival knowing which allows you to
solve problems that you can't solve
without perspectival knowing. You can
pick up on the world. The world
discloses itself in ways that it is not
otherwise disposable to you. And then
consciousness emerges as an optimization
on the formation of episodic memory. So
it is optimally transfer appropriate for
the future. Right?
And then you get
It is a sense of agency, but it's not a
billiard ball agency. It's the it's this
kind of longitudinal agency. And to tell
you the truth, given the human
critiques, that's actually the kind of
agency the self has. It has this kind of
longitudinal
uh right agency around episodes. It
doesn't have this I'm an some sort of
uncaused cause a moved mover within
myself which I think is both a
ridiculous proposal ontologically and an
and an ethically
undesire why would I want such a thing
right it it's like it's completely
arbitrary I I think my life is being
lived I'm trying to change myself so
that I am my thoughts are as determined
by what is true my action as determined
by what is good and my perception is
determined by by what is beautiful as I
possibly can. I would like to lose all
my freedom in that sense. Um and so I
think if we move to the right level of
analysis and Gallagher makes a
convergent argument about this that when
we're talking about agency and self,
we're not talking at that limit scale.
We're not talking at where's the first
movement of the billiard ball chain.
We're talking more about No, no, no. How
are we building this long-term virtual
engine that enhances our predictive
agency in the world?
Yeah, absolutely. And that and
Gallagher's work is very convergent with
Thomas Matzinger's of course. Uh and so
this just for our audience this these
arguments and this notion of the
narrative of self is well fleshed out in
active inference literature. Um, so I
could point you. Yeah, I would probably
start with the the Fris and Limonowski
papers. There are two wonderful papers
about self- construction under active
inference.
And and then I have a convergent
argument coming out of Daniel Daniel
Huda who is also in the 4E, right? The
narrative practice hypothesis. And he
argues that any mindsight ability, any
ability to see in other people's into
other people's mental states, you know,
attributing beliefs and desires to them,
uh, requires, well, for example, if I'm
going to attribute a belief and desire,
I need to know something about your
character.
Yeah.
Are you lying or not? Right. I need to
know something about the context, the
setting, what like what's going on in
this situation. Are you tired? Is that a
small child? So, you're not really lying
when you tell them at Christmas time
that there's a Santa Claus, right? Uh,
right. And and and I need to know what
the conflict is, what the problem.
Notice what I'm talking about here. I
need to know all the elements of
narrative. Right.
Daniel Kudo points out, we practice
narrative incessantly. And unlike many
of the other things, including language,
which we scaffold for children, we
scaffold narrative for our our kids. I
had to sit through the Teletubbies twice
in which you have to sit through these
really impoverished narratives because
we're scaffolding this up because
narrative ability gives us the right
gives us the set of skills the sets of
states of mind with the perspectives
taking therein and the traits of
character that allow us to pick up on
other people's mental states and I think
that is also a function of the self the
function of selves is to make us
agentically predict addictive to each
other.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. And there's
another there's another convergent
argument in active inference which is
that um only in the context of other
people like you would you ever come to
the inference that there is something
that is like to be you like
if you were alone
converges with that converges with the
whole Vagotssky approach to the
development of metacognition and
self-awareness which I think is right
right right and of course um your
colleague at um just pointing people in
different directions your colleague at
Toronto or former colleague do you want
Peterson um yeah
has a whole uh literature on literature
and narrative and he has a conversation
with Carl on his podcast which is um
deeply intriguing about these kind of
alignments of the free energy principle
and and narrative. John I wanted to also
speak about flow states. Um
you've written about flow as yes the
sort of locus of implicit learning. Um,
as you know, I've just been writing up a
paper on flow, um, from an active
inference perspective. So, I'd love to
be able to sort of see maybe where we
align, where we don't align, and try and
sort of unpick that. Just as a
forewarning, my paper, the paper that
I've written with my wonderful
co-authors is not out yet, but it should
be coming out soon. Um, so
I want to I have not yet read your paper
because you you suggested waiting. Uh,
yes, the paper's gone through. um
modifications as papers are want to do.
Um it's in the final stages. So you you
have access to it. So so please feel
free to read it.
I will read it then. I will read it for
I can give I can give a very brief
overview. So to not disadvantage you um
my the basic thesis of the basic
perspective that we take on the paper is
about selfmodeling under flow states. So
that's the main thing that we're looking
at and the attenuation of an epistemic
agent model
because what we're arguing is that
certain precision waiting mechanisms are
lending it are
leading the organism to undertake
pragmatic action seeking out pragmatic
affordances
um rather than engaging in what Carl or
other authors would call epistemic
foraging. Now I think where we might
have a point of difference is I have a
section on flow states and learning
and I think this is a really interesting
point because your paper speaks about
implicit learning whereas I'm
and and this and to to make it
transparent this is there are I've heard
different perspectives on this but my
current opinion is that in flow states
what you're getting is a reinforcement
of the skills that you actually um
picked up through epistemic work. So I
have the example of a violinist. The
violinist must undergo a certain period
of exploration of epistemic foraging
which comes with this kind of self-t
talk this real prominence of myself as a
knowing thing.
Yeah.
Right. And then what it does is over
time through learning you get high
precision um over the beliefs about that
action in terms of the technical detail
and then that becomes kind of the
foundation on which you can then go and
do more epistemic work and then that
become and then that expertise
development is stepwise in a sense I
mean you can picture it either way but
critically and where we differ is that
I'm arguing that actually in the moment
of flow itself you're just garnering
more evidence for the capacity ities and
the policies that you already have.
So I I'd like to start there and see and
see what you think of that claim.
Um so we as you point out uh Leo Ferraro
Arian Perenadi we argue um something
different um which is why you're
bringing it up. Uh we argue that um um
that learning is inevitably occurring
even in the flow situation and so
there's improvement. Um and that's why
if the environment doesn't have the
capacity to renew uh its challenges on
you, you will very quickly fall out of
the flow state. So the argument is well
why don't you just stay in the flow
state? Well the argument is because
eventually you get a mastery over the
environment um which means your skills
start to exceed the demands. And so
phenomenologically when I'm in the flow
state like in sparring or lecturing um
I'm finding tremendous amount of insight
and innovation uh coming out um
now this is where it might get tricky um
because is procedural innovation a
restructuring of especially uh is that a
restructuring of um uh your information
and therefore have new capacities in it
new emergent abilities
or is it just a reinforcement? And I
don't this we might get into Thesius's
ship here which is be problematic.
Uh but
the one of the defining phenomenological
features of the flow state
and I'm uh I want to be clear I'm not
pinning you down on this but I do think
it's relevant evidence is the ongoing
sense of discovery. There's a sense of
discovery there. There's a sense of
coming to know things you did not know
before. And of course, when the flow
state is in much more comprehensive
expertise, not like with playing tennis
or maybe like just your optimal gripping
on the world, people come to think they
have learned something deeply profound
[clears throat] uh about reality. So, I
tend to think that there's evidence for
transformative learning happening up and
beyond just reinforcement learning.
Okay. Yeah. I I I like the return to the
phenomena. Um, you know, Drafus has this
phrase which I will definitely use over
and over again in this podcast which is
when in doubt return to the phenomena.
Um, the way that we have cast it is that
there's this idea in the literature
about a hyper prior that the world is
changing. So that we have a prior that
the world is changing and that is
adaptive for us because we don't get
stuck in the same free energy minima.
Now if that prior is always at play,
what ends up happening downstream on
that is that my
inference about my own abilities
deteriorates over time and we and we we
experience that I guess. I mean like if
I play tennis today and then I play
tennis in a week's time, I'm probably
going to have less fidelity in my own
capacities in a week's time than I do if
I play tomorrow having followed today.
Yeah. And so our argument is that the
positive a effect that's part of the
flow state is downstream on the surprise
that's generated when you actually
violate that hyper prior that the world
is changing because what you're getting
evidence for is that your policies still
work in a world that you would have
infer you would have thought didn't lend
itself to your policies working and
there's this idea um Casper Hesp's paper
and his co-authors in 2021 that affect
in active inference is about um
basically your model doing better than
you thought it would do. Um, and and
this actually comes a lot into what Mark
talks about in terms of aerodynamics.
So,
I'm wondering if uh
Yeah. Well, I don't know. [laughter]
Yeah. Yeah.
Well, see, I I think that's right. I
think and and and the problem of course
is you can get an infinite regress. So,
well, I'll say, well, the model the the
things here and you'll say, well, there
needs to be something a a hyper prior
behind that. And then we can That's what
I mean about Thesius's ship.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So again, I would say, well, what what
are you getting better at? And what
you're getting better at, I would argue,
is
um not stand like so expertise is
generally built around like uh giving
you a well like a a specific domain. We
can talk about um the possibility of
sort of meta expertise if we want, but
what I mean by that is once you've got
expertise, you've gotten really good at
within a certain domain at formulating
the problems you're fronting as for you
well- definfined problems. Uh that's one
way in which an expert is sort of
reliably different from a novice. A
novice goes in, this is an ill-defined
problem. The expert goes goes in and
says no, it's this problem and this is
the what you need to do and this and
this and this and this and this. Okay.
So, we agree with that. But I think
what's happening, right, and and maybe
this is the gray area between your
position and mine. I think what's
happening is we're discovering new ways
in which we can turn well- definfined
problem, sorry, illdefined states into
well- definfined problems. We're going
something like I didn't realize I could
adapt to that situation, but I can.
And and that sounds similar. Uh but for
me, that's that's an insight experience.
Uh and that's what like it's an inside
flow because you're you're you're
getting an extension of your cognitive
capacity because you have restructured
what you take to be the like your abil
your your problem formulation of the
world. That's that's uh
yeah I mean to supplement that I I
actually I I don't disagree um on that
note but the way I would formulate that
and this actually isn't in the paper.
It's in the paper in some sense, but
it's not a fully fleshed out argument
because it wasn't hyper relevant.
I'm glad there's another really quality
paper on flow coming out.
There's not there's really there's
really nothing. Um, when we published
the paper, we were the literally the
only paper talking about the cognitive
processes that work in flow.
I I yeah, it's it's a it's a bizarre
one. Um, there's very little on skillful
coping generally within
cognitive science. But I as I said I
think that's why I said there should be
more phenomenology
activ or cognitive science co
convergence.
What what we kind of mentioned in brief
is that flow if we take the sort of
macro perspective on what flow is it
could also be this kind of humming
between the pragmatic and the epistemic
boundary.
Yes. So maybe when you're realizing, oh,
I can reframe this um kind of uh
perplexing problem as actually something
manageable, what you're doing there is
maybe just slightly exiting the flow,
doing some epistemic foraging, returning
because something I want to make really
clear to everyone listening as well. the
when we talk about epistemic action and
pragmatic action in terms of expected
free energy or active inference it's not
like the agent goes I'm doing pragmatic
action right now and I'm doing noic
action right it's part of the actual
maths right so if you looked at the
maths
it's like
firstly you can do a bit of both right
at the same time like that that's a
thing
but it's also like the action policies
that we're talking about here John and I
these are not protracted seven hours of
just like pragmatic action. No, no.
These have to be very temporally thin
because the world is volatile, right?
The world is constantly changing and so
you have to be able to not just pin all
your hopes or put all your eggs in one
basket in terms of an action policy. And
so actually fundamentally our divergence
might well be a semantic thing which is
that I'm talking very much about the
synchronic nature of being in flow right
now and like I have for for simplicity I
have that boundary between pragmatic and
epistemic whereas if you take a kind of
more macro perspective as that flow
state as the conerto unfolds you could
be humming at that boundary and doing
learning as well. Yeah, I I I I really
look forward to your paper because I
think that sounds like actually a
powerful way in which the theories could
be integrated uh together. Um, I'm also
interested in a question that's emerging
out of this disc. Well, I I've already
been interested in this question, but it
emerges out of what we're talking about
because I'm interested because I I think
there's there might be an additional
thing um
because there's you can flow in a in a
situation and it doesn't transfer it
doesn't transfer to other domains. Video
game addiction is the classic model. You
can flow in the game, you can't flow in
the world, so you get depressed in the
world. you could flow in the game and so
you want to stay in the game more and
more and more
u that for that's very different than
how I flow in Taichi Chuan Taichi Chuan
in fact other people pointed this out in
me the the flow states that I cultivate
in Taichi Chuan I can they're cultivated
in such a way that they transfer broadly
and deeply to many other domains and I'm
interested in the this this this sort of
ritual framework because what what you
get is this ritual and this
philosophical framework Dowoism and
other ecology other practices and
ecology of practices around so that it
broadens um like it transfers in
powerful ways and and I'm wondering um
what the differences are
and also if how does that show up is
there a phenomenological difference
there I mean so now really really really
anecdotally right uh in terms of
phenomenological practice I do get a
sense of a difference with between when
I'm just flowing and when I'm flowing in
a ritual context. So if I enter into a
violin hall and like let's say I'm an
expert in playing the violin and I see a
crowd and I see my violin and I see the
whole stage what I end up getting is
this um so habits are quite well
codified within active inference you get
this kind of contextual cue that like in
layman's terms although this is we're
saying this isn't happening
propositionally it's time for me to play
the violin and this can look like
precision over beliefs about your own
action. So what this is again not
something I've thought about necessarily
with any depth because this is just
something that you've brought up. I'm
wondering whether that contextual cue
what you're happening when you're doing
taichi and then maybe what you're doing
when you're lecturing is that your your
your
system is seeing similarities in that in
the contexts and doing similar precision
waiting in other in in a separate do in
a separate domain.
Yeah, I think that's right. And I think
what philosophical frameworks do is they
reverse engineer that. They try to uh
find out what might be similar or maybe
even invariant across many contexts and
then build that back into the specific
context in which you are doing the
practice to exactly afford that transfer
appropriate processing. I think that's
right. I think there's something else
also going on with the queueing and this
goes into a's metamotivational theory.
We can be we can be broadly speaking we
frame our arousal in two different ways.
When we're in itelic mode and we're
working towards an some where where the
reward is found in the external goal
then increased effort is experienced as
frustration and and it and then if it
increases too much I get anxiety. But I
mean if I'm doing something where the
goal is the behavior itself like making
love or doing poetry then the increased
not infinitely obviously but the
increased arousal is framed as positive
as excitement. Right. Right. Right.
Right. uh and so I think also and so
actor talks about safety uh safety
framing right let's call the first
itelic mode work and the um the
paratelic mode um um
play and I think ritual has to do with
serious play and I've got a whole
argument about that but I think also
what what you're doing in the context is
you're queuing you're trying to queue
people into the play mode uh because the
play mode allows them to model
themselves their arousal as positive
rather than as negative and that allows
them and I think there's a deep
connection between this parellic framing
and chick set's
I think accurate claim that flow is
autotellic doing it for its own sake
right yeah yeah cool yeah I I like the
notion of effort here recognize that one
of the fundamental factors or
fundamental characteristics of flow is
uh perceived effortlessness
yes even though you can even though you
can sort of very uh peripheral cues that
you might be expending a lot of
metabolic energy.
Exactly.
Um and just for the given this is the
active inference institutees podcast
just for those interested in the
computational framing of that within
active inference Thomas Parr has got a
paper out this year on cognitive effort
and active inference. So that gives a
kind of nice computational modeling
picture of that which actually leads me
to a much broader question because I
know we're we haven't got too much more
time which is I've noticed in myself to
be totally candid that I've started like
I I learned about flow and success
through you and and through other people
but mainly as a philosophical notion um
and now I'm viewing it as a
computational notion.
Yes. Yeah. Do you worry about that? Do
you worry that if we rely too much on
comput not not just computational models
but maths, physics, we in some ways
reduce the phenomena in a way that's
detrimental. Not just because it's not
romantic or that it's but like that
we're missing something fundamentally.
Well, it depends. I mean, that's a
really important question. We could do
two hours on just that question. Uh but
if you think that a leveled ontology is
actually the way ontology is um uh that
the level at which we do science is as
ontologically real as the quantum level
we discover when we're doing science.
And I think you have to come to that
conclusion and I have extended arguments
for that elsewhere. Then u there's then
you can make a clean philosophical
distinction between explaining away in a
reductive fashion and explaining that
actually enriches your appreciation for
the phenomena. Uh now if the
computational stuff the computational
stuff to my mind well let's say what the
argument we were just exploring um has
merit then notice what we're saying.
We're saying well what the computational
modeling actually does is actually shows
why this sometimes very obscure
philosophical framework is really
important. Yeah. It's actually doing
some really important work and you can't
get rid of it. You can't dispense with
it. and and and and and and that would
mean that kind of some of the stuff
we're doing where we're trying to
commodify flow and take it out of those
those frameworks and you know and do the
thing we do and you know sell books and
right um it's actually mis
misrepresenting the phenomena in a in a
in a way that we can philosophically and
scientifically critique and say wait
right this phenomena has the power it
has because chickmat sahai said it's an
evolutionary marker for adaptivity and
then well making it adaptive is how
broadly and deeply is it transferring
out of the situation and then the
philosophical framework really matters
to what it is and how it functions and
so if you if you can make a distinction
and you need an onlogical distinction to
make this distinction but if you can
make a distinction between explaining
and explaining away then then I think
it's possible to say no no no when I do
these things and and to be fair to me
Darius I get a lot of people who, you
know, are from various religious and
spiritual backgrounds and they come in
and they say, "Thank you so much for
your work. I now I much better
appreciate
this,
this experience or that experience or
the flow state or this mystical state
because you didn't try and tell me it's
nothing but you tried to say this is
what it's doing and this is why you like
it and value it so much."
But do you think your work
to kind of Yeah. to look at that
personal vantage point. Do you think
you've managed to keep like because if I
without being sort of embarrassingly
lording
people should watch Awakening from the
Meaning Crisis um not only for the
content but also just the way you
present it which is just so magical. Um
so thanks. I mean it's it's really
inspired a lot of the way that
I think science should be done and
philosophy should be done. What what is
it about? I think you know anyone who
watches that recognizes there's
something kind of special going on
there. The ideas are living through you.
You're they're breathing through you're
breathing through them. There's this
really beautiful coupling. Again, we'll
come back to that between you and the
ideas.
What What is it about that kind of
synthesis of the philosophy and the sort
of more hard cognitive science? do you
think made that project so successful?
I suppose it's a view of the role of
cognitive science, what cognitive
science is doing. Um
I think what cognitive science does is
it's
well I I'll try and do it sort of
narratively uh uh and I do this in the
series. I think you know the even the
notion of mind if we've been invoking
mind and cognition is equivocal uh
because it means one thing to the
neuroscientists who's studying the brain
and looking at uh neurons and anatomical
networks and perhaps functional
networks. means a different thing to the
artificial intelligence person who's
building algorithms and huristics
um and doing reinforcement learning and
blah blah means a different thing to the
psychologist who's studying human
behavior with experiments and running
stats and they talk about working
memory. They don't talk so much, right?
And it means a different thing to the
linguists and a different thing to the
cultural anthropologist. By the way, I
include them because they were the
people that have been studying
distributed cognition and collective
intelligence. They matter.
Yeah. Um, now if you think about it on
this analogy, it's like they're
different countries speaking different
languages. And here's the thing, and
that has great value. Specialization has
great value. I'm not dismissing that. I
am not dismissing that. But each one of
these is talking about a different
level. And here's what I think I would
state as a very plausible claim. I think
it's unlikely that these levels in
reality the brain information processing
behavioral linguistic socioultural
levels are independent from each other.
I think they causally influence and
constrain each other. So we are missing
something important about the mind by
right not getting clear about the
relationship between these levels. can
be equivocating and we are we have a
fragmented notion if we don't capture
the relations of constraint and
causation between these different levels
of cognition and mind and so I think the
proper function of cognitive science is
to use philosophy's skills of
creating bridging discourses creating
bridging conceptual right uh vocabulary
theoretical grammar so that these
different disciplines can talk to each
each other in reciprocally
reconstructive ways as a way of
converging on the causal and constraint
relationships between the levels rather
than trying to compete or say the bottom
level is the only real real level. So
that for me they all live together. They
are doing and I'm sorry to invoke it
again. They're doing opponent processing
between each other.
Um and that's how that's that's what
that's that's what inhabits me when I'm
doing cognitive science that vision. I
call it synoptic integration.
Yeah. It's it well it's wonderful to
see. Um so so I mean like I think we I
mean that's the cognitive scientist that
I'm aspiring to be. Um I think you've
called it a big picture cognitive
scientist as well.
Yes. And one of the things one of and I
felt very lonely for a while you know I
I was doing relevance realization which
is a big picture and then to my great
delight another big picture for ecod
side came down the and then to my even
greater happiness another big picture
came down the road which is you know the
predictive processing framework and I
think they are more convergent than uh
adversarial and I well you've heard me
arguing about how we can integrate them
together. Excellent. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
would say maybe it's just bias.
Active inference is or physics
processing is a big picture cognitive
scientist from from the physics and the
maths all the way well what we're trying
to do to the phenomena
to what it is like to be a to be a human
being to have conversations like this.
John, it's um I it was you know I can't
say it was better than I expected
because I knew it was going to be
wonderful. But um you're full of just
thrilling insights and speaking to you,
listening to you is always such a
wonderful learning experience whether
that happens in flow or without flow. Um
but I just wanted to thank you so very
much for I know you're extremely busy um
but for giving us your time. Where can
people find you? What have you got
coming up? Um I'm sure people are
curious. So the most immediate thing for
this conversation um is the talk I gave
at Leiden on the predictive processing
symposium. It's up on my channel. I
think it's the second most recent video
on my channel on YouTube.
You can put it in the
Yeah.
where I I I try to go into the nuts and
bolts of how you could integrate uh
predictive processing and relevance
realization theory together. So people
might find that and I've got a lot of
good feedback on that uh for being sort
of clear clear and and a good argument.
Um so I I would recommend that when
people are interested in uh the the the
the broader implications of this um
awakening for the meaning crisis and
then after Socrates also uh after
Socrates is where I take all of this in
all of this stuff and well how do you
turn it into practices in order to
overcome self-deception and enhance
relevance realization become more wise
and virtuous um and so they can take a
look there u the arguments around
neoplatanism
Um there are several videos around that
and how I try to connect neoplatanism to
forecogi and relevance realization and
predictive processing as as we saw in
this podcast. But in the neoplatinism,
I'm working on my third big series um
walking the philosophical silk road,
which will be on Zen neoplatanism,
trying to see if we can bring an
integration, an opponent processing, not
an adversarial one, an opponent
processing between Zen and Neoplatanism
to give us a rich philosophical
framework by which, like the
philosophical road, we could trade ideas
and move between worlds without um
having to descend into well tribalism.
and other such things.
Wonderful. Wonderful. Well, again, it
was absolutely my pleasure. I apologize.
I've got a slight cold, so if I've been
a little sniffly or nasal, um
blame it on the we can blame it on the
London weather, but um I'd love to have
you back on at some point. Um your your
work is is truly inspiring. So, thank
you so much, John, from me and the
institute.
Thank you, Daryus.
I'm happy to come back on and you know
if it if it turns out that you know Mark
and I come on together that would be
thrilling as well.
Great. We will definitely get that
sorted. All right. Thank you.
Thank you.